Hello and welcome to our Business
Central Launch Event for uh
2024 release wave one.
Uh we will talk about new brand new
feature sustainability inside the
Business Central. And before we start,
let's first introduce ourselves. So,
my colleague
Yes. Hello, my name is Volodymyr Synchuk
and I work as software engineer. I
worked on this sustainability project.
Yeah, thank you, Volodymyr. And my name
is Aleksandar Totovic. I'm product
manager responsible for this
functionality.
Let's shortly explain what is our agenda
for today.
Uh first, we will explain why we started
with this feature at all, then our
strategy and architecture about it.
After that, I will show some basic
foundational part and then Volodymyr
will continue with full end-to-end demo.
Okay.
Um
Why we started with this feature? Why we
need this feature at all? And before I
start, I want to
uh start with sustainability drivers.
Okay, first of all, um
we want to be as greener as possible.
And probably all of us we want to leave
better planet for our children.
But
there are other business drivers for
going in into sustainability
um except only the social. So, let's
start with first.
Very often, we have customers who want
to to work only with if not totally
green, but as greener as possible
companies. Then further, we have very
often investors
and they are thinking very often that
they do not want to invest for a future
if company is not sustainable and
enough.
Then very often now we have new
generation and employees can choose
company if based on their sustainability
investment, not only on our profits.
And the last, but not the least, are
regular regulations.
And now when we talk about regulation,
we can split these four pillars or four
drivers. First three, they are, let's
say, voluntary.
Um if we have this kind of customers,
investors, employees, we need to take
take care about that. But if not, yes,
we can still
uh wait few years to start to be more
sustainable. But on the other side, if I
have regulation and regulation are
enforcing us to be more sustainable and
to report it,
this is not the question. We must go
there. So, let's look what we have about
regulations across the world. I will not
explain everything. I cannot go in into
every country, but just the most
uh
regulation we are most familiar with.
First, I will start with European Union
and in European Union we have now CSRD
Act. Uh if we start for 2024, it is
starting with 2024 reporting in this
year for the biggest companies. Then we
have we still don't have we will have
because date is still not
published in UK.
Something similar we have in US and
Canada. Dates are still not actually for
Canada we have date, but in the United
States this is still not published when
it will start, but very often companies,
especially bigger companies, thinking on
investors, they are starting to record
emissions. Then further, we have India.
Uh we have in Australia, New Zealand and
I said I don't want to limit only on
these few countries, so there are much
more
regulations across the world. And some
of these countries are countries where
Microsoft has official localization,
Microsoft based localization. In some
others, we have partner based
localization. But we wanted to make
something already enough for even for
partner based localization, so they can
continue easily to build their own
localization on top of that.
Now,
um
let's focus what is, let's say,
the
primary focus for Microsoft because the
most of Microsoft localizations are in
the European Union.
And now I will briefly focus on what is
the most important for these countries
to comply as there is a new regulation
behind the door.
Um we have already mentioned CSRD new
act.
Uh this is
related with European
um requirements for
for the most of companies.
Uh this is non-financial public
disclosure and this is connected with
ESG or environmental, social and
governance.
So,
uh which companies will be affected?
Right now, with current situation, that
means before new enforcement,
approximately 11,700 companies, a little
bit more than that, are affected with
this regulation. But with new regulation
starting from the next year, more than
50,000 companies in across the European
Union will be affected with CSRD rules.
So, this is really important because
there are huge number of Business
Central customers and they will need
uh to report uh sustainability
for CSRD.
Now, before I continue, I just want to
explain shortly difference between
sustainability functionality embedded
inside the Business Central. This is for
SMBs. And on the other side, Microsoft
Cloud for sustainability or
sustainability manager.
Um
What is the main difference? Microsoft
Cloud for sustainability or
sustainability manager is intended for
bigger enterprises.
This is great uh solution, a really
great, amazing one. But on the other
side, let's say, 80% of our customers
are in SMB, small and mid-size size. And
for them, it will be too complicated to
work in a different environment, very
often different environment,
um too complex to track all these
things. So, we decided to build
something relatively easy for tracking
in a well-known user interface, that
means inside the Business Central. And
it will be
uh it will be it is planned for SMBs.
Now,
um let's look in a time frame and
companies in the scope. Uh first,
um some information about CSRD existed
before this year. And they started to
track this earlier. This is not
something we started to track this year.
And um
why we decided to deliver now? Because
all these changes are starting with this
year.
Um
you can see for 2025th,
but this is for reporting, but it will
be applicable for this year. This is for
the biggest companies listed on um
uh listed on stock markets. So, we can
still say this is definitely this is not
our focus. Business Central is not a
solution for this size of companies. But
what is our focus? Main focus is
something what is coming in 2027 for
reporting, but that means we must
tracking for 2026.
And in the
in the middle you will see 2026 for
reporting, but that means you need to
start to track this
uh
information from next year. What is
about? This is for, let's say, a little
bit bigger, larger companies with more
than 250 employees.
So,
um
this is still not maybe our main focus,
but we have a lot of companies there in
this segment. So, we wanted to deliver
some minimum viable product until then.
So, these bigger companies who are using
Business Central, they can start track
their
uh sustainable
uh emissions and to track them and to
record them. But our main focus is to
deliver in next four waves what is
really mandatory to have for our um
especially smaller companies with more
than 10 employees. So, you can see if
this is more than 10 employees, uh the
most of our customers will be affected
um
with this regulation. So, they must
track their changes from 2026, beginning
of 2026.
Now,
when we talk about Business Central
sustainability,
let's see what we can track and what we
can track. Actually, how far
uh sustainability journey can go. In
total sustainability journal, we will
start with recording, reporting, but
reducing, removing, and replacing. This
is full sustainability journal uh
journal journey.
But um Business Central cannot deliver
everything. So, we are focused in our
first waves to record and report.
It doesn't mean maybe we will not extend
in some moment to maybe to even reducing
with some ideas, with some
recommendations, maybe. But now we are
focused on recording reporting.
Now, let's look in
our strategy and architecture.
Uh before we go technically, I want to
explain our strategy scope
for this first wave.
In this first wave, uh we will focus on
greenhouse gas emissions and we will
support three emissions with the biggest
impact.
Carbon footprint, uh but also methane
and nitrogen dioxide.
Uh we will
Okay, we will not be limited only to
them. This is what we have right now in
this scope. It can be extendable by you
as a partners. It can be extendable
potentially in the future by ourself,
but this is what we are supporting right
now. But when we talk about scopes in
greenhouse gas emissions, there are
three scopes. And first scope is
actually
um
what company reporting. This is about
internal company transport,
some company pollution and so on in
company uh facilities. Then we have
scope two and scope two is indirect.
So, comparing with previous one who is
direct, this time this is indirect scope
and it comes from upstream and this is
mostly connected with power plants,
streams, some similar voices you will
get from your vendors. But then there is
the biggest scope, scope three, indirect
scope three
and this is reserved for upstream and
downstream activities. You will see
there is
purchase goods, sell good, transport,
business travels, many, many different
types of sustainability
topics you need to track.
Now, let's look in a process flow.
Um as I said, this functionality is
multi-wave investment. That means we
didn't finish that we didn't make
everything in this wave. This is
multi-wave investment and the idea is to
have minimum of value product before we
start the following year. So, this
minimum value product will be finished
with the next wave.
So, let's see what we have in this
release. In this release we deliver
foundational part for sustainability, so
everything will go much easier further
because this is the most important. If
you do not have proper foundation, we
cannot continue
uh with further development.
First,
what we have for tracking data, we have
sustainability journal and we have both
of types. We have recurring
journal and we have journal, so if you
uh have
recurring um
emissions, you can easily use recurring
journal. Of course, there are journal
batch, journal template, everything
based on a standard we are using for
other journals inside the Business
Central. Then
uh we have some um
some category, sub category, but
connected with a chart of sustainability
account. You can see the name. This is
still chart of account, but we just
added chart of sustainability account.
The same structure, but just different
things. We don't measure
um some financial impact, but we measure
our emission impact.
Um we have these connected categories
and subcategories. I will explain a
little bit more later
um
for which they are intended and we have
different calculation to calculate
calculations and formulas, so we can
easily calculate our emission if you do
not know exactly amount of emission.
And then, yes, all of them they will go
to sustainability journal lines and once
we have them, we can use standard
posting procedure. Everything will
finish in sustainability ledger entries
from where we can report. Right now we
have some standard reports there, but in
the future we will add some
uh regulatory reports as well.
What we will have more on the top of
that, it will come probably in next one
or two minors, we will enable all these
entities through APIs.
So, this is important, so we do not want
to limit uh partners or customers to use
only what is inside the Business
Central. Yes, we have
I think really good foundation. We will
extend it with more functionality. Our
ISVs will add probably much more on the
top of that, especially about industry
specifics, but if you have some external
source or external solution and you want
to connect with Business Central, it
will be really easy to connect through
APIs. So, you can continue your
development inside the Business Central
or outside of Business Central.
About foundational parts, what we have
inside, I will just briefly explain
because Vladimir explained much more in
details through demo.
First,
where I will start. I will start with
Contoso demo tool.
Why I start with demo tool? Because we
added sustainability module in demo
tool.
I think we think this is a great
beginning how to use it because
sustainability functionality in general
is
pretty new for all of us, for us in
Microsoft, but for you as a partner and
customer, this is pretty new topic and
very often you cannot show all these
details, you cannot understand, maybe we
cannot understand sometimes and because
of that we we decide to make good
sustainability demo data module,
so you can immediately start, especially
if you want to present to your potential
customers, so everywhere you can easily
start with that and you can show
everything what is inside. You will have
chart of sustainability accounts, but I
just need to emphasize this is not some
regulation based. This is just demo.
Just for demo purpose. You can use this
for tracking, but you can
short it if you if you want, if you
don't need all these details, but you
can even use 10 times more data there if
you need. So, this is just our vision
for demo demo demo purpose. Then you
will have already configured categories
and subcategories there.
Um
you will have
already sustainability journals with
already populated
lines, so you can easily understand how
to use it and you will have already
posted sustainability ledger entries, so
you can immediately start to start from
reporting. You can run report, you can
show what is inside, so
I think we have this great great demo
data.
Then, let's start from the beginning. We
have sustainability setup. In
sustainability setup you can configure
different unit of measure for different
sustainability needs. Um
For example, you can you will have two
unit of measure, one for regular
tracking data, but tomorrow when you
you still have enforcement reporting,
maybe it it will come in three years,
depends from country to country and
right now you do not know if you need to
report in tons or kilograms and you just
started to to track and you you are
tracking in kilograms and maybe
regulation will be that you must report
in tons. You can just choose different
unit of measure for reporting and you
will have factor, so you can easily
translate there. You can find some
rounding, decimal places, mandatory
usage, for example, you can use
mandatory country or region or
responsibility center if you want to
track if your company is in different
countries, if you want to report based
on different facilities, then further
you can block
or enable some functionalities.
My colleague Vladimir will explain this
in demo, so I will not go so deep in
details.
If you look in a chart of sustainability
accounts on the first sight,
you will see that it look as a standard
chart of account. This is just for
sustainability needs.
You can track different emission types
and what we have there, we have for each
of accounts we have category where you
can determine which kind of scope you
want to track with this
account, then which kind of emissions
you want to track there because you are
not a force to track all three
emissions. You can choose based on this
on
every account you want to track, you can
you can decide if you want to track
only, for example, a carbon footprint or
you want to track all of them. Then even
further you can add type of calculation
because if you do not know right
emission amount, you can use different
calculation, so it will be much easier
for calculate what you need to report.
And sustainability
subcategories, you can add emission
factors based on emission you want to
track in categories.
In journals, as I said, this is
relatively easy. This is standard
journal
just for sustainability
purpose. You can track you can record
all your emissions. You can post. You
have different type of entry data. I
mentioned a few times uh if you know
your emission,
uh you can choose manually amount,
manually input amount and you can enter
your
emissions manually. If you do not know,
you can, for example, you know your car,
your distance or fuel consumed and
formula will calculate automatically
based on emission factors.
Um yes, we have batch per scope. You can
uh you can configure batch to be per per
scope, but you can use as a common and
we have some good tool for checking if
you have a potential issue, but Vladimir
will explain more in details.
About reporting and this is the last I
will show you
as introduction.
Uh this time, yes, we deliver three
reports. You will see total emissions,
emission per facility, emission by
category, but
what we can say about them, you will see
extra layout here on the screen. All
these three reports are
first made to be by Excel layout and
layouts, default layouts are Excel
layouts.
RDC exist, but Excel layout will be by
default. So, we are looking in Excel
layouts much more serious and we want to
start, especially if you want to
not to make document, if you just want
to
to check some statistic, some entries,
this is much better for you for using.
And as I mentioned, regulatory reports
are still not here.
This is something what will come in the
future.
So,
now,
um Vladimir,
you can continue with your
great end-to-end demo, so
people will see everything how it's
looking in a practice. Thank you,
Alexander. Uh yes, let's start by
generating some demo data and as
Alexander said, it is uh
part of our Contoso demo data module.
So, let's go here and
choose sustainability model. As for all
other models, we can generate just a
setup data or generate it all like setup
data and transactions.
So, let's generate it all.
And then, yes, we want to post some
journal lines to get some entries to
explore
uh our features.
So, yes, now we have demo tool
executed.
Uh let's
jump to sustainability setup.
Here, we set up basic settings like unit
of measure, decimal places, some
validation parameters, some error
handling, and some reporting,
rounding, and other parameters.
From here, we can also
set up our account categories that we
will have a look a bit later.
And subcategories.
Also, in the same way as in other areas,
we can set up a journal template
and journal batches.
Both like normal and recurring journal
templates.
Now, let's
have a look at chart of sustainability
accounts.
It has the similar structure as chart of
general ledger accounts with totaling
and heading and posting accounts.
And
also, it has, of course,
some
default flow filters,
date dimensions,
responsibility center, so you can use it
in two filter the totals.
And yes, each posting account
contains some basic data, some balances,
and some set up data.
Where set up data is category.
Let's just have a look at category.
So, here we define our scope.
We define calculation foundation.
And then we define which emission do we
want to report. So, this information
will be used in sustainability journal
to calculate your emission based on
whatever foundation you have. This
formula is extendable, so if you have
other needs, you can extend it.
On a subcategory,
we define our emission factors.
Those are also used in calculation in
journal.
Now, let's have a look at journal.
Our journal is done in the same way as
other standard
BC journals.
Batch, lines, background error check
that shows you
the lines with errors.
So, now yes, and also some set up
information that you can see here. So,
now let's try to post.
We get an error.
Right, let's try to correct it.
I know it's this line. So, our emission
section is empty.
So, let's see what this line is about.
So, this account is emission scope one.
Calculation foundation distance, and we
see that it is CO2 and CH4 that has to
be reported.
Let's just enter some
mileage in here.
And our emission is already calculated
here. So, we can post this line. But we
can see that next line is missing unit
of measure.
This is purchase services, so let's add
our
And then
we also see the error that
it also needs some emission to be
specified.
Since this line
has manual input check mark,
we can go ahead and enter our emission
directly into the line.
Now we post.
And yes,
now we got this information in
sustainability ledger entries. Same way
as in GL functionality.
The last thing to show is our reports,
which are available from chart of
sustainability accounts.
We have three.
As Alexander said, we decided to go with
Excel layout.
Our DC layout is still there. You can
use this one, but our default now is
Excel.
So, let's just run this one.
And open file.
Yes, some security warnings.
And now
you see we have a nice pivots and
charts. So, this one, for example, shows
you permission per scope. You can play
around with it. This one has some
slices, so you just
yeah, can filter to whatever you need.
And this one contains some nice charts
with total emission split.
Yes, we
have three
reports
that you can play around. And yeah, I
guess that's it for this demonstration.
Alexander, you want to take it over?
Yeah, thank you, Vladimir.
Um
Before we close this session, I just
want to wrap up what we have here. That
means first,
we deliver the as the first foundational
part. Our functionality is still not
everything what we will deliver. So,
this is multi-wave investment. Then,
what we deliver right now? We deliver
sustainability chart of account, nice
functionality. We have sustainability
journal,
and using different categories, emission
formulas, and so on, so on, you can
easily use manually data you have, or
you can use this format to calculate
your emissions. Once when you post all
this information, it will finish in a
ledger entry, sustainability ledger
entry, and
you can use
great reports in Excel layouts.
Even you can easily extend, add
additional charts if you need. So, we
think this is the right direction for
reporting. And you all can expect very
soon APIs, so you can easily connect
with this solution from any outside
solution.
Now, before we close this session, I
would like to invite you
to
come to our Yammer group, AKMSBC Yammer,
to have open communication with
everything, not only about
sustainability. Yes, we have
sustainability channel in this in our
Yammer, but we can talk about
everything. Join our additional
conversation on Twitter, actually on X.
Some other social networks. But
what I will definitely suggest, if you
see something is missing, definitely, as
I said, this is foundation, so probably
some things are missing. And we have our
backlog, but we are counting on your
feedback. We want to hear from you what
you want to get more in sustainability.
Not limited to sustainability, but
please about sustainability, go to
AKMSBC
Ideas, and just send us idea. We will
evaluate all of them. We will discuss on
Yammer about these ideas, and we will
make future scope together. What we
think is missing in the system, and what
you think is missing.
Again, I will
ask you to join on a monthly
office hours. So, every month we have
interesting topics, and if you cannot
remember all of them, just try not to
forget this one
at the bottom, AKA AKMSBC
All. So, you can find all resources
there. So, you can easily find all these
nice URL
for getting more information, more
resources.
Okay.
Now, on the end, I can just say thank
you, and I hope we will see in live on
Q&A session.